Finding Aid for Neil Staebler papers, 1944-1992
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Neil Staebler papers
1944-1992
Staebler, Neil, 1905-
85817 Aa 2 AC
Ann Arbor, Michigan, businessman and attorney, chairman of the Michigan Democratic Party State Central Committee, U. S. Congressman-at-large, 1963-1964, gubernatorial candidate in 1964, member of the U. S. Federal Election Commission, 1975-1978. Chronological, congressional and topical files relating to political and personal activities; include political files detailing state election campaigns 1948-1964, particularly the campaigns of G. Mennen Williams and John B. Swainson; also photographs and transcript of oral interview, 1979.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
319.5 linear feet
2 oversize volumes
Neil Staebler (Donor no. 2417 ) began donating his files to the library in 1961.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
During the post-war period in Michigan politics, the state Democratic Party experienced a renaissance in voter acceptability. Roughly corresponding to the six term administration of Governor G. Mennen Williams (1949-1961) and in. part attributable to his extraordinary popularity, the Democratic Party underwent an about face and became a model of sorts for other state party organizations.
The successful architect of the party's victorious campaigns in this period was Ann Arbor businessman - politician Neil Staebler. As chairman of the Democratic state central committee, Staebler together with a group of dedicated and energetic aides spear-headed the party's transformation. Staebler believed that for the party to be successful it had first to formulate and espouse a liberal program geared in part to the state's large work force. Secondly, Staebler argued that for the party to succeed at the polls it needed to organize strong precinct level organizations capable of eliciting grass-roots support for the party's program and turning out the vote on election day. With this formula, Staebler helped the Democratic Party to capture the governor's office for seven straight terms and to elect Democratic senators, Patrick McNamara and Philip A. Hart.
With two major exceptions, Staebler shunned elective office. These two campaigns, however, account for some of the more interesting portions of the collection. In 1962, Staebler was elected congressman-at-large, an office which was something of an anomaly because the state's two political parties had been unable to incorporate the additional Congressional seat which Michigan received as a result of the 1960 census without fighting over the necessary redistricting. In 1963 or 1964 Staebler made the decision to become a one-term Congressman, seeking instead to run for governor against the incumbent George Romney. From all outward appearance, Staebler had a better than even chance of victory. The national ticket of Johnson and Humphrey appeared destined for a landslide victory, and Staebler could not help but benefit from their coattails. Unfortunately for the candidate, his opponent George Romney, was a strong campaigner and a popular governor, and he won reelection easily. Following his defeat, Staebler returned to the routines of party work. He continued to be a member of the Democratic National Committee; he was a member of the Democratic National Finance Council, and the National Democratic Charter Commission; and he was appointed to the Federal Election Commission in the 1970s.
Summary Contents List
Chronological files, 1949-1970 -- Boxes 1-16
People files -- Boxes 16-46, 272-278, 284-298, 300, 315-318
Congressional files -- Boxes 47-66 Congressman-elect correspondence -- Box 47 Subject files -- Boxes 47-51 Government departments and agencies -- Boxes 52-56 Legislative files -- Boxes 57-63 Topical Files -- Box 64 Miscellaneous -- Boxes 64-65 House Committee on Science and Astronautics -- Box 66
Campaign files -- Boxes 67-115 Non-Staebler campaigns, 1948-1974 -- Boxes 67-78, 82, 103 (part), 104 Neil Staebler: Congressman-at-large campaign, 1962 -- Boxes 79-81 Neil Staebler: Gubernatorial campaign, 1964 -- Boxes 83-103 (part) Candidates files, 1948-1973 -- Boxes 105-115
Political files -- Boxes 116-221, 313-314, 319 Forms (copies of party mailings) -- Boxes 116-122 Conventions -- Boxes 123-135 Campaign Directories and related materials -- Boxes 135-136 Campaign Platforms and Convention Resolutions -- Boxes 136-137 Democratic State Central Committee -- Boxes 138-175, 309-310 Democratic National Committee -- Boxes 176-190, 311-312 Michigan Governors/Senators files -- Boxes 191-196 Calendar-Invitations -- Boxes 197-206 Federal Agencies and Departments -- Boxes 207-209 Miscellaneous -- Boxes 210-221, 313-314, 319
Federal Election Commission files -- Boxes 222-240, 306-308
Issues files -- Boxes 241-258, 301-305
American Veterans Committee -- Boxes 259-260
Speeches and Articles -- Boxes 261-262, 320
Ann Arbor Citizens Council -- Boxes 263-266, 322
Personal and Miscellaneous -- Boxes 267-271, 281-283, 321
Visual Materials -- Box 279
Neil Staebler first began donating his files to the Michigan Historical Collections of the University of Michigan in 1961 following his eleven year tenure as chairman of the Democratic Party State Central Committee. Periodically thereafter and continuing into the 1970s, Staebler continued to add to his collection with Congressional papers (1963-1964), campaign files when he ran for governor in 1964, topical records created from his years of service with the Democratic National Committee (see attached vita), and records from his term as commissioner on the Federal Election Commission (1975-1978).
This collection comprised of twelve series documents Staebler's career and the course of Democratic politics since World War II. Since Staebler was principally an organizer of campaigns, a behind-the-scenes manager who preferred to handle the details of an election rather than to step into the candidate's spotlight himself, the collection concerns all phases of a successful campaign not just the posturings of the party's candidates. There is, for example, much information relating to the day-to-day operations of the party, i.e. fund-raising activities, the annual Jefferson-Jackson Day Dinner, the formulation of the party's platform and related resolutions at the Spring and Fall conventions, and the activities of party-related special interest organizations.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Democratic Party (Mich.); Democratic Party (Mich.). State Central Committee.; Elections--United States.; Elections--Michigan--1948.; Elections--Michigan--1950.; Elections--Michigan--1952.; Elections--Michigan--1954.; Elections--Michigan--1956.; Elections--Michigan--1958.; Elections--Michigan--1960.; Swainson, John B. (John Burley), 1925-1994.; United States. Congress.; United States. Federal Election Commission.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1960.Elections, 1960.; Presidents--United States--Election--1960.; Elections--Michigan--1962.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1962.Elections, 1962.; Elections--Michigan--1964.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1964.Elections, 1964.; Presidents--United States--Election--1964.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Cavanagh, Jerome Patrick, 1928-1979.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Politics and government--1946-1960.; Politics and government--1961-1970.
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.
- Chronological file, 1949-1970
  The Chronological Files series consists of duplicate carbons of all of Staebler's outgoing correspondence. This chronological file dates from September 1949 through 1970.
  - September 1949-December 1950 (Box 1)
  - January-December 1951 (Box 2)
  - January-October 1952 (Box 3)
  - November 1952-December 1953 (Box 4)
  - January-December 1954 (Box 5)
  - January 1955-July 1956 (Box 6)
  - August 1956-July 1957 (Box 7)
  - August 1957-November 1958 (Box 8)
  - December 1958-March 1960 (Box 9)
  - April 1960-December 1961 (Box 10)
  - January 1962-August 1963 (Box 11)
  - September 1963-November 1964 (Box 12)
  - December 1964-June 1966 (Box 13)
  - July 1966-March 1968 (Box 14)
  - April 1968-April 1970 (Box 15)
  - May-December 1970 (Box 16)
- People files
  Throughout his career, Staebler maintained a People File, consisting of correspondence and other materials arranged alphabetically by name of individual or organization. There are currently two large alphabetical subseries to the People File plus several boxes of files awaiting interfiling into the two sequences.
  - 1950s-1960s
    - A-Am (Box 16)
    - Am-Be (Box 17)
    - Be-Br (Box 18)
    - Bu-Ch (Box 19)
    - Ch-Ci (Box 20)
    - Ci-Co (Box 21)
    - Co (Box 22)
    - Co-Dem (Box 23)
    - Dem-Det (Box 24)
    - Det-Dz (Box 25)
    - E-Fo (Box 26)
    - Fo-Gr (Box 27)
    - Gr-He (Box 28)
    - He-In (Box 29)
    - In-Jo (Box 30)
    - Jo-Ko (Box 31)
    - Ko-Lo (Box 32)
    - Lu-McG (Box 33)
    - McG-Mi (Box 34)
    - Mi-My (Box 35)
    - N-Nat (Box 36)
    - Nat-Ol (Box 37)
    - Om-Pr (Box 38)
    - Pr-Ro (Box 39)
    - Ro-Sc (Box 40)
    - Scr-Sp (Box 41)
    - Sp-Sy (Box 42)
    - T (Box 43)
    - U-We (Box 44)
    - We-Wo (Box 45)
    - Wo-Z (Box 46)
  - 1970s-1980
    (includes much material prior to 1970)
    - A-Gallagher (Box 284)
    - Gal-Hall (Box 285)
    - Hal-Hol (Box 286)
    - Hom-Ju (Box 287)
    - Kaa-L (Box 288)
    - Maa-Michigan (Box 289)
    - Michigan-National (Box 290)
    - National-Power (Box 291)
    - Power-Ros (Box 292)
    - Roz-Sheraton (Box 293)
    - She-Std (Box 294)
    - Stea-Tillette (Box 295)
    - Time-Walch (Box 296)
    - Walt-Williams (Box 297)
    - Williams-Z (Box 298)
    - People (to be interfiled) A-Z (Box 300)
    - People (to be interfiled) (Box 315)
    - People (to be interfiled) (Box 316)
      (continued)
    - People (to be interfiled) (Box 317)
    - People (to be interfiled) (Box 318)
    - People (to be interfiled) (Box 272)
    - People (to be interfiled) (Box 273)
    - People (to be interfiled) (Box 274)
    - People (to be interfiled) (Box 275)
    - People (to be interfiled) (Box 276)
    - People (to be interfiled) (Box 277)
    - People (to be interfiled) (Box 278)
- Congressional Files, 1963-1964
  Staebler's Congressional Files were accumulated from his one term in the U.S. House of Representatives, 1963-1964. This series consists of subject files, executive department and agency files, and committee files. This series includes files from Staebler's work as member of the House Committee on Science and Astronautics.
  - Congressman-elect correspondence
    - [A-Z], November 1962-January 1963 (Box 47)
  - Subject files
    - [A-C] (Box 47)
    - [D-K] (Box 48)
    - [L-P] (Box 49)
    - [P-R] (Box 50)
    - [S-Z] (Box 51)
  - Government agencies and departments file
    - [A-D] (Box 52)
    - [D-H] (Box 53)
    - [I] (Box 54)
    - [I-L] (Box 55)
    - [M-Z] (Box 56)
  - Legislative files (arranged by committee)
    - [A] (Box 57)
    - [B-I] (Box 58)
    - [I-J] (Box 59)
    - [J-M] (Box 60)
    - [N-V] (Box 61)
    - Ways and Means (Box 62)
    - Ways and Means (Box 63)
    - Miscellaneous legislation (Box 63)
  - Topical files
    - [A-Z] (Box 64)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Form responses [arranged by subject and agency name] (Box 64)
    - Regional office files (Box 64)
    - Speeches (in HR; extension of remarks in HR) (Box 65)
    - Speeches (outside HR) (Box 65)
    - National Issues Forum miscellanea (Box 65)
    - Card file index to NS congressional files (Box 65)
      (in boxes 66A-66B)
  - House Committee on Science and Astronautics
    - Miscellanea (Box 66)
    - Press releases (Box 66)
    - Legislation introduced (Box 66)
    - Miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 66)
- Campaign files
  One of the largest series is Campaign Files. Here the researcher will find all of the records relating to state elections beginning in 1948 and to Staebler's own campaigns in 1962 and 1964.
  - Non-Staebler campaigns
    (see also oversize scrapbook of clippings and some photographs relating to Staebler and the Democratic Party, 1950-1963)
    - 1948-1950 (Box 67)
      (include earlier collected campaign material, and material concerning 1950 election recount)
    - 1951-1952 (Box 68)
    - 1952 (Box 69)
      (include material concerning 1952 election recount)
    - 1952-1954 (Box 70)
    - 1954 (Box 71)
    - 1954-1956 (Box 72)
    - 1956 (Box 73)
    - 1956-1958 (Box 74)
    - 1958-1960 (Box 75)
    - 1960 (Box 76)
    - (G. Mennen Williams), 1960 (Box 77)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 78)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 82)
      (include election statistics, 1964)
    - (no 1965), 1966 (Box 103)
    - 1966-1974 (Box 104)
  - Neil Staebler: Congressman-at-large campaign, 1962
    (see also oversize scrapbook)
    - Topical files
      - [A-I] (Box 79)
      - [I-S] (Box 80)
      - [S-Z] (Box 81)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 81)
      - Card files
        - Petition circulators, 2 boxes (Box 81)
        - "Friends" (Box 81)
  - Neil Staebler: Gubernatorial campaign, 1964
    - Detroit office
      - County files (mailing lists, correspondence)
        - [A-R] (Box 83)
        - [S-W] (Box 84)
      - County field reports (Box 84)
      - Miscellaneous files
        - Derengoski, Robert A. (Box 84)
        - Burnette Staebler schedules (Box 84)
        - Huber, May (Box 84)
        - Union support (Box 84)
        - Massachusetts Ballot (Box 84)
        - Young Democrats (Box 84)
        - General information (Box 84)
        - Democratic chairmen-mailing lists (Box 84)
        - Steering committee chairmen (Box 84)
        - County steering committees (Box 84)
        - Registration (Box 84)
      - Staff files
        - Nancy Beaulieu (Box 84)
        - Joseph Crafton (Box 84)
      - Task forces (Box 84)
      - Fact Sheets control (Box 84)
      - Forms (Box 84)
      - Regional organization files [arranged by color code] (Box 85)
      - "Responsibilities of Staebler Chairman" and coordinators (Box 85)
      - Mimeo office control (copies of distributed material), January-October 1964 (Box 85)
      - Outgoing correspondence, February-November 1964 (Box 86)
      - Copies of correspondence from Ann Arbor and Washington, January-September 1964 (Box 86)
      - Office procedure miscellanea (Box 86)
      - Detroit Area Representative files
        - Area control (Box 86)
        - Areas (arranged by no.) (Box 86)
        - Field Representatives (Box 86)
      - Hearings
        - Education (Box 86)
        - Mental health (Box 86)
        - Senior citizens (Box 86)
        - Economic growth (Box 86)
      - Speakers Bureau (Box 86)
      - Subcommittee lists
        - Agriculture (Box 86)
        - Business and professional (Box 86)
        - Educators (Box 86)
        - Finance (Box 86)
        - Labor (Box 86)
        - Lawyers (Box 86)
        - Senior citizens (Box 86)
        - Veterans (Box 86)
      - Volunteer Operation (Box 86)
      - Volunteer files (Box 86)
      - General campaign information
        - Campaign directory control (Box 86)
        - Special events (Box 86)
        - Platform (Box 86)
        - Newsletters (Box 86)
        - Press releases (Box 86)
        - Delegates (Box 86)
      - Invitations (accepts and regrets)
        - April-October 1964 (Box 87)
        - October 1964 (Box 88)
      - Invitations (miscellaneous) (Box 88)
      - Schedules, 1963-August 1964 (Box 88)
      - Schedules, September 1964 (Box 89)
      - Schedule books, February-November 1964; 4 volumes (Box 89)
      - Schedules (miscellaneous) (Box 89)
      - Events, March-October 1964 (Box 89)
      - Date books, 1963-1964; 2 volumes (Box 89)
      - Miscellaneous files re. finances, events, and fund-raising (Box 90)
    - County files
      - [A-S] (Box 91)
      - [T-Z] (Box 92)
    - Press releases, 1963-1964 (Box 92)
    - Washington files
      - Topical files: [A-L] (Box 92)
      - Topical files: [M-Z] (Box 93)
    - Alphabetical files: [A-P] (Box 94)
    - Alphabetical files: [P-Z] (Box 95)
    - Congressional districts (Box 96)
    - Campaign-Finances and issues (Box 96)
    - Subject file (Box 96)
    - Subject file (cont.) (Box 97)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 97)
    - Annette Hodesh files (Box 97)
    - Miscellaneous topical files (Box 97)
    - Campaign notebook (Box 97)
    - Card files
      - "Friends" file: Detroit and Wayne County (Box 98)
        (cards contain name, address and specific information regarding contributions given, work done or skills)
      - "Friends" file: Alcona-Lenawee (Box 99)
      - "Friends" file: Livingston-Wexford (Box 100)
      - Miscellaneous index cards (Box 100)
      - Thanks for contributions [A-Z], 4 boxes (Box 101)
      - Thanks for work; congratulations, 3 boxes (Box 101)
      - Microfilm of name card file, 2 microfilms (Box 101)
      - Prospects, 2 boxes (Box 102)
      - Volunteers (Box 102)
      - County card file (Box 102)
    - Volunteer and visitor sheets and notebook (Box 102)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 103)
  - Candidates file
    - 1948-1952 (Box 105)
    - 1952-1954 (Box 106)
    - 1954-1956 (Box 107)
    - 1956-1958 (Box 108)
    - 1958-1960 (Box 109)
    - 1960-1963 (Box 110)
      (No file for 1964; see Staebler gubernatorial campaign files, boxes 83-103)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 111)
    - 1966-1968 (Box 112)
      (No file for 1967)
    - 1968-1970 (Box 113)
    - 1970-1972 (Box 114)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 115)
- Political Files, 1950-1975
  Political Files detail Staebler work as chairman of the Democratic State Central Committee (1950-1961) and his work with the Democratic National Committee notably as national committeeman (1961-1964, 1965-1968, and 1972-1975). This series has been subdivided into various subseries. Among these are: Forms (chronologically arranged copies of the materials mailed out of the State Central Committee office); Convention files which concern local, state, and national Democratic Party conventions; Directories and Platform files; State Central Committee files relating to the work and divisions of the state's Democratic organization; Democratic National Committee records; files concerning the relationship between the SCC and state Democratic leaders, primarily G. Mennen Williams, John Swainson, and Senators Hart and McNamara; Calendars/Invitations files; Federal agencies and departments files concerning the relationship of the state party to the federal government; and Miscellaneous files.
  - Forms
    (copies of party mailings)
    - July 1950-1952 (Box 116)
    - 1953-September 1954 (Box 117)
    - October 1954-July 1956 (Box 118)
    - August 1956-October 1957 (Box 119)
    - November 1957-December 1958 (Box 120)
    - 1959-February 1960 (Box 121)
    - March 1960-January 1961 (Box 122)
  - Convention files (county, state, national)
    - 1950-1952 (Box 123)
    - 1952-1953 (Box 124)
    - 1954-1956 (Box 125)
    - 1956 (Box 126)
    - 1957-1958 (Box 127)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 128)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 129)
    - 1961-1964 (Box 130)
    - 1965-1968 (Box 131)
    - 1969-1972 (Box 132)
    - Delegate certification lists, 1950-1956 (Box 133)
    - Delegate certification lists, 1956-1957 (Box 134)
    - Delegate certification lists, 1958-1960 (Box 135)
  - Campaign directories and related material, 1950-1975
    - 1950-1960 (Box 135)
    - 1961-1975 (Box 136)
  - Campaign platforms and convention resolutions (state and national), 1948-1970
    - 1948-1955 (Box 136)
    - 1956-1970 (Box 137)
  - Democratic State Central Committee, 1950-1975
    - Minutes, 1950-1965 (Box 138)
    - Meetings, 1949-1957 (Box 138)
    - Meetings, 1957-1973 (Box 139)
    - Meeting notices (Box 139)
    - Chairman's files (Box 140)
    - Assistant State Chairman (Box 140)
    - Deputy Chairman (Box 140)
    - Vice Chairman (Box 140)
    - Chairman's assistants (Box 141)
    - Secretary (Box 141)
    - Treasurer (Box 141)
    - Board and officer meetings (Box 141)
    - Subcommittee files (Box 142)
    - Business and professional committee (Box 143)
    - Conferences and meetings
      - Miscellaneous (Box 143)
      - Western States Conference (Box 143)
      - Midwest Conference (Box 144)
    - Detroit office files (Box 145)
    - Lansing office files (Box 145)
    - Policy Committee, 1950-1972 (Box 145)
    - Field trips and Field office (Box 146)
    - Field trips and Field office (Box 147)
    - Correspondence with Congressmen (Box 147)
    - Topical file: [A-E] (Box 147)
    - Topical file: [F-P] (Box 148)
    - Topical file: [P-Z] (Box 149)
    - General and unsorted (Box 150)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 150)
    - County files (incomplete), 1963-1972 (Box 151)
    - Long Term Planning Committee, 1961-1962 (Box 152)
    - Political Reform Commission, 1968-1970 (Box 152)
    - Organizations (Box 153)
      - Federation of Democratic Women (Box 153)
      - Women's Division (Box 153)
      - Women's Day (Box 153)
      - Young Democrats (Box 154)
      - Teen Democrats (Box 154)
      - Republican State Central Committee (and Republican National Committee) (Box 154)
    - County-district papers, 1950-1951 (Box 155)
    - Congressional district files, 1951-1952 (Box 155)
    - County-district papers, 1952-1956 (Box 155)
    - Congressional district files, 1955-1956 (Box 155)
    - County files [A-E], 1956-1958 (Box 155)
    - County files [F-W], 1956-1958 (Box 156)
    - Congressional district files, 1956-1958 (Box 156)
    - County files [A-W], 1958-1960 (Box 157)
    - County files [W], 1958-1960 (Box 158)
    - Congressional district files, 1958-1960 (Box 158)
    - County files [A-V], 1960-1962 (Box 158)
    - County files [W], 1960-1962 (Box 159)
    - Congressional district files, 1960-1962 (Box 159)
    - Organization plans, 1951-1952 (Box 159)
    - County files [A-L], 1956-1960 (Box 160)
    - County files [M-W], 1956-1960 (Box 161)
    - Publications
      - Topical files (Box 162)
      - Topical files (Box 163)
      - Printed material (Box 163)
      - Printed material (Box 164)
      - Fact Sheets (Box 165)
      - Program Service (Box 165)
    - Patronage files
      - Wayne County: Include correspondence concerning political appointments and organization, 1951-1955 (Box 166)
      - Patronage files: Post Office appointments (Box 167)
        (sample; other series discarded)
    - Reference books for County Democratic Leaders (Box 167)
    - Finance Office
      - 1950-1952 (Box 168)
      - 1952-1953 (Box 169)
      - 1954-1956 (Box 170)
      - 1956-1958 (Box 171)
      - 1958-1961 (Box 172)
      - 1962-1971 (Box 173)
    - Jefferson-Jackson Day Dinner
      - 1949 (Box 173)
      - 1950-1956 (Box 174)
      - 1957-1975 (Box 175)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 309)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 310)
  - Democratic National Committee, 1950-circa 1968
    - Correspondence, 1950-1956 (Box 176)
    - Nationalities Division, 1952-1956 (Box 176)
    - National Jefferson-Jackson dinner (Box 176)
    - Democratic National Conference and Jefferson Jubilee, May 1950 (Box 176)
    - Conferences, meetings, and dinners (Box 177)
    - National campaigns, 1852-1961
      - Presidential election, 1952 (Box 178)
      - Presidential election, 1956 (Box 178)
      - Presidential election, 1960 (Box 179)
      - Inauguration, 1961 (Box 179)
    - Advisory Committee on Political Organizations (Box 180)
    - Advisory Committee on Political Organizations (Box 181)
    - Advisory Committee on Political Organizations (Box 182)
    - Advisory Committee on Political Organizations (Box 183)
    - Charter Commission (Box 184)
    - Charter Commission (Box 185)
    - Advisory Council (Box 185)